Now let's talk about security a little bit,
imdi gvenlik hakknda biraz konualm,
let me log in again. As you learned,
tekrar giri yapalm. rendiimiz gibi, bizim
we manage our auth state here with the token and we automatically log the user in if we have a valid
auth durumumuzu belirtele ynetiriz ve geerli bir belirteimiz varsa, kullancy
token. That token is only valid for 60 minutes though, that is for security reasons
otomatik olarak giri yaparz. Bu jeton sadece 60 dakika boyunca geerlidir, yani gvenlik
because if the token gets stolen, anyone can access your data of course,
nedenlerinden tr nk eer jeton alnrsa, herkes elbette ki verilere eriebilir,
now that sounds very bad.
imdi bu ok kt geliyor.
Keep in mind though it's stored in your application in local storage, local storage can be accessed with
Yerel depolama alannda uygulamanzda depolanm olmasna ramen, yerel depolama alanlarna apraz site komut dosyas
cross-site scripting attacks and cross-site scripting attacks are prevented by Angular, you can't output
saldrlar ile eriilebildiini ve Angular tarafndan apraz site komut dosyas saldrlarnn nlendiini unutmayn, varsaylan olarak
insecure code by default.
gvensiz kod ktsn alamazsnz.
So you got a lot of protection from that side,
Bu nedenle, bu taraftan ok fazla koruma
so your data and local storage should be safe, an additional safety net then is again that the token
aldnz, bu nedenle verileriniz ve yerel depolama alannz gvenli olmal, ek bir gvenlik a daha sonra bir
expires after one hour.
saat sonra semboln sona ermesi demektir.
Now firebase would theoretically also give you that refreshed token if we inspect the response we get
Artk firebase teorik olarak size geri dndmz cevab incelediimizde
back, here
bu yenilenmi
that refresh token. The refresh token doesn't expire,
jetonu da verir. Yenileme jetonunun geerlilii sona
you could store that too in local storage and then there is a specific end point on the firebase auth rest
ermez, yerel depolama alannda da depolayabilirsiniz ve kimlik kodu iin yenilenmi bir jeton
API where you can exchange a refreshed token for an ID token, you just send your refreshed token
deitirebileceiniz, firebase yetkisiz geri bildirim API'sinde belirli bir biti noktas bulunur. Yalnzca yenilenmi jetonunuzu buna gnderirsiniz.
to this API endpoint and you get back a new ID token.
API biti noktas ve yeni bir kimlik jetonu geri alrsnz.
Theoretically that's a cool pattern,
Teorik olarak bu harika
you can always do that with every HTTP request you send, with every request you send you send an
bir modeldir, her zaman istediiniz her HTTP isteiyle bunu yapabilirsiniz, size gnderdiiniz
additional one where you exchange your refresh token for a new ID token even if the ID token hasn't
her istek ile yeni bir kimlik jetonu iin yenileme jetonunuzu deitirdiiniz ek
expired yet
bir tane
so that you always get new ID tokens and you could also get a new one when the user is automatically
gnderiniz. Her zaman yeni kimlik belirteleri aldnz ve kullanc otomatik olarak
signed in with the functionality we added over the last lectures, I opted to not use that here.
son derslere eklediimiz ilevsellik ile oturum aldnda yeni bir tane alabildiinizden, bunu burada kullanmay semedim.
It's also safe because we can store the refresh token in local storage and as I mentioned, this is only
Ayn zamanda gvenlidir nk yenileme kodunu yerel depoda saklayabiliriz ve bahsettiim gibi, bu yalnzca
accessible with cross-site scripting attacks.
apraz site komut dosyas saldrlaryla eriilebilir.
Still, having a token which never expires and which you can exchange for a token which gives you access
Yine de, hibir zaman sona ermeyen ve her eye erimenizi salayan bir jetonu
to everything could lead to security issues or at least you should be very careful about protecting
deitirebileceiniz bir jetona sahip olmak gvenlik sorunlarna yol aabilir veya en azndan yenileme belirtecini kullanyorsanz
it if you are using the refresh token.
onu korumanz konusunda ok dikkatli olmalsnz.
That's just something I wanted to add,
Bu sadece eklemek istediim
you can enhance the user experience by using the refresh token, you can essentially make sure the user
bir ey, kullanc deneyimini yenileme belirtecini kullanarak gelitirebilir, temel olarak kullancnn hibir
is never logged out because as the refreshed token never expires, you can refresh the main token even
zaman oturumu kapatmadndan emin olabilirsiniz nk yenilenen jetonun sresi hi bitmeden, ana simgeyi bir hafta
after a week
sonra bile yenileyebilirsiniz.
just check for the token being valid, it isn't,
Jetonun geerli olup olmadn kontrol edin,
take the refresh token and get a new one but due to that security thing,
deil, yenileme jetonunu aln ve yeni bir tane aln ancak bu
I opted to not use it and I wanted to bring this to your attention.
gvenlik nedeniyle, kullanmay semedim ve bunu dikkatinize sunmak istedim.